can I
meditate watch your
breath e
come to the Goen
room e
like to play a little bit with the
feeling of losing the object I have this
theory that if
we can replicate purposely what it feels
like to lose the object maybe we would
notice it more
easily when the time comes
so come to the golden room and then I'll
ask you to think of
dinner and then I'll take you back to
the golden room and then I'll take you
to dinner and I just want you to feel
what it's
like to be constantly
interrupted by Gua by
agitation stay in the golden room
bring your llama before
you have them touch your hands
think of dinner what might be for
dinner picture the cafeteria picture the
people Ming
around picture the serving
dishes come back to the touch of your
llama's h
feel that sense of the
mind
uh withdrawing inwards towards a core
when you try to bring your attention
back you're on your Lous hands
now think of arriving at your
home on Sunday or
Monday coming in the door things you
have to do
come back to n's head
think about the people in your
COV who makes
noise who you'd like to talk two
more come back to Al with him
think about your job your work what you
do for
money what you going to have to do in
the next few months
what bills you
have then come back to
now Focus just on your llas head in the
golden room relax into it
enjoy the touch of their hands the
warmth of their hands
feel contented as if you could stay in
that room for an hour two
hours just quietly holding
come back to their
headp e
come back to this
room and open
your I think you feel how unpleasant it
is here it's like
someone bothering you right I it was
really hard for me I was thinking it's a
bad sleep
so
uh but it's good to know what it feels
like it's it's very disturbing and
tiring
right I'd say that was that was a
recreation
of
level one
right okay I was trying to do more time
off the object than
on uh but anyway play with that
sometimes
identify within your own mind the
different states of mind we're talking
about
identify the state of mind
that that catches a problem the the the
watch do state of mind then try to it's
hard for me identify the state of mind
that pulls your mind
back uh because it's very sudden for me
it's very sudden and then try to play
with uh n like focus on the other
without L and then bring some L up and
see how the how it feels different okay
if you can't do those things at will
then you won't be a good meditator you
have to at will you have to be able to
identify those states of Mind within
your mind
okay and in time you'll get to know them
like friends and you'll be able to evoke
them when you need them okay okay we
have a box of questions here
okay this
okay I'll read the whole thing okay you
dear holy Lama you defined real as
something that appears the same way that
it exists unreal would therefore be an
object which appears different than how
it actually exists Buddhist scripture
also uses the phrases deceptive reality
and Ultimate Reality to describe the
same process what about the word
Duality is the original meaning of the
word Duality the same as unreal and
deceptive
reality uh this word Duality seems to be
used in different ways with Western
Scholars writing about Buddhism can you
clarify including the idea that
everything is one in the lovey doy
hippie
sense
uh
yeah the the word Duality is one of my
pet peeves in in in Buddhist
translation
uh I can only think of one one word in
Scripture that they might be translating
I don't know but that's called Nang Nang
means uh it does refer
to something looking one way appearing
to be one way and being actually a
different way so which which is what
deceptive reality refers to Okay so
deceptive real Buddhism does Define two
different kinds of reality one is called
deceptive reality and one is called
Ultimate Reality deceptive
reality is that reality which is fooling
you all the time
okay it's
the gaka reality it's the pen that
appears to be coming from itself it's
the
nick uh who doesn't deserve to get
blamed okay uh those um
that's the way things appear to us okay
they appear to us to be coming from
their own side but then in reality
they're not they're coming from from us
so that
discrepancy is called Duality N N means
two appearances so in Buddhism the word
is n n
means it looks one way and it is another
way okay it it seems like especially to
Nick Under
Pressure that
uh that there's a Nick who doesn't
deserve to be
criticized
uh but in reality there's no never a
Nick who's criticized who didn't deserve
it by definition okay
um so the discrepancy between those two
is called deceptive reality and that's
what Duality means in in in Buddhist
philosophy um
people have tried to draw a
distinction of Duality between the
object and the subject right the subject
state of mind and the object state of
mind
um and they've tried to say that that's
somehow uh wrong that it's wrong for me
to think that I'm over here and the
object is over there like I'm here and
the paper is there and that's that's a
that's some kind of a bad Duality okay
there's still attempts to to say that
that's what Duality means or that or
that that's what Buddhism meant Duality
to be I'm not aware of any Buddhist
school that holds
that you know there's none of the
classical schools of
Buddhism would
say uh that there's any problem with
saying that I'm over here and the
paper's over there you know uh and that
we are not one okay uh the word for
object is y
desha and uh which also means a place
like Bangladesh or uh and then
um the word in in all all of the
Classical Languages of of of Asian
Philosophy
for for subject is that which holds the
object okay
desin that which possesses an object so
or in tibetan you chin so there's not
even a separate word for object object
is defined by being that thing sorry
subject is defined as being that thing
which holds an object to so to say
somehow that the subject is the
object uh is just not there's no uh
School of Buddhism which would say that
it's a misunderstanding I don't know who
got got that I don't know where it comes
from uh the the direct experience of
Ultimate Reality is sometimes described
as uh like pouring water into water okay
the subject becomes engrossed in the
object in the way that water is poured
into water and they become indivisible
okay uh that doesn't mean that you
become what you're meditating on or
something like that okay that's a that's
a new agism or I don't know where it
came from uh it's not it's not part of
any classical school that I that I know
about so you
are uh during the direct perception of
Ultimate Reality you can no longer
distinguish yourself from the
object because you are not Ultimate
Reality a person Mike Mike's mind Mike's
body these are not Ultimate Reality
these are
changing uh changing ephemeral
things uh they're not Ultimate Reality
Ultimate Reality actually is a absence
of something okay absence of what gaka
okay Ultimate Reality is the absence of
a g
Ultimate Reality is the absence of a
Nick who didn't deserve to be I'm sorry
yeah who didn't deserve to be blam okay
that's Ultimate Reality
so when you're perceiving Ultimate
Reality
directly uh you can only perceive those
things which are in absence of gaka
that's all you can perceive you can't
perceive anything
else uh you can't even be aware of
yourself at at at that moment because
you are immersed in an absence of
something okay and you are not an
absence of something you're a positive
thing uh so during the say 20 minutes of
your first direct perception of Ultimate
Reality uh your mind is absorbed into
the object in the way that water is
poured into water and and you can't be
aware of yourself because you are not an
absence of the gaka okay you're not
Ultimate Reality
that doesn't but that's not a overcoming
Duality or something like that that's
just a bad understanding okay it doesn't
mean that Mike is the emptiness that
Mike is watching it just means that it
just means that when Mike is engrossed
in The Emptiness he can't perceive Mike
but that doesn't mean that somehow Mike
is the object okay so subject and object
that division
is that's not what Duality refers to so
classical Duality only means
uh the discrepancy between how things
appear and what and how they really are
and that's throughout and you can
overcome that kind of Duality
okay that's
all
[Music]
okay I think I'll go to the text cuz I I
but I'll show in questions when you seem
to get uh sleepy okay here we
go so they were talking
about okay you could talk i' have you do
it do in your mind
okay that's the definition of Ana or
impermanence in uh in Buddhism a thing
which is instantaneously coming in and
out of existence every moment it is
coming in and out of existence then uh
they were saying that if Nick were his
body and his mind okay if Nick were his
body and his mind all physical things
and all mental things are are are are
impermanent in the sense of uh changing
Instant by instant they come in and out
of existence Instant by instant why they
are being sustained by your mental seeds
and your mental seeds go off 65 per
second so
the the frame is being uh what do you
call it the frame is being put up in
front of your mind and then it's being
taken away in the next frame it's like a
movie okay it's like this and then you
have the illusion of of motion okay uh
so the question here was if when we're
looking for
Nick uh Nick is his body for example
then Nick should
Nick Nick should be uh going in and out
of existence Moment by moment okay Nick
all
right and he would have to be suddenly
different each time so you'd have to
call him a different
name okay he'd be Nick one Nick 2 Nick 3
Nick four Nick five you see what I mean
uh he had he's subtly different each
time
uh so you couldn't use the same word for
each momentary appearance of him you see
you'd have to have different words like
Nick John Tim Ted you see what I mean he
wouldn't be one
Nick right he'd be all these little
Nicks who came in and out of
existence right
P okay I didn't know if I I told you
yesterday there's something I didn't
want to get
into but you're all fresh and all that
so the cold are getting
better you know originally people have
asked if they could have some more
exercise originally this we were
supposed to do walking meditation but we
were afraid people would you know break
their necks
and then we had the camp set up work for
you guys like fixing fences and stuff
but they're all under snow right
now uh but I have an idea that they
could clear the road actually that's
what in Boy Scouts that's what they did
when they want to keep us out of trouble
they'd say clear this road
boys and
uh the road out is very dangerous right
now I took it yesterday to pick up my
llama and it was very dangerous so I
think uh
you know maybe we could go work on that
so we I'll look into it with the
authorities all right uh
anyway uh I thought that since you're
all
chipper uh we could go a little deeper
all right
uh so we we've been examining whether uh
Nick comes from his own
side we had a class like this in Sarah
okay and gion took the took the named
Tashi there was a guy named Tashi and
then uh we talked about Tashi for
weeks and then uh we all went to G
tantry College because one of my
teachers had become the Abott there and
we were trying to talk him about some
top secret
books which he didn't give
us and which later we sent in a Tibetan
lady from the computer center and she
just walked out with him and we
talk uh but uh I'm not supposed to tell
that that
um then
uh the vice abbit came to we they had an
honorary dinner for us and the vice
abbit came in and with he was very you
know sort of I don't Know full of
himself and then he said my name we want
to Welcome All You Americans to the
greatest Ted most in the world and I'm
of course I'm the vice th and my name is
tshi
and then everybody started run and he
was very
offended it's like he comes in and says
I'm n you know and we've been looking
for
[Music]
n so we've been we've been trying to
find a Nick which maybe we could start
to call Natural R shinga okay uh a Nick
which was natural
meaning uh a Nick which was inherent in
the part of Nick or you could say if you
want to make it easy a Nick which is
coming from his own side okay anck which
had to be that way independent of the
kic seeds in my mind independent of how
I've been treating other people uh he's
Nick and he's a certain kind of Nick
okay and we've been saying that that
Nick is a is a gaka okay that kind of
Nick doesn't exist
the Nick which is Nick from his own side
doesn't exist the only Nick which exists
is the Nick which my seeds are forcing
me to
proceive all right any other Nick is not
there although I I strongly feel that
it's there and that's the cause of all
my problems
um so let's talk about the Nick who is
there right the one the one which I'm
creating with my mind uh does he have a
relationship to his parts
yeah right we were talking I mean the
ultimate example is the pot on the stove
right and there's a round silver and
there's a long black
and and we we've come to the conclusion
that there wasn't a part on the stove
but that I was watching a picture in my
mind but does that picture in my mind
have a relationship to the to the round
silver and the long
black yeah I mean it's it's it's placed
onto that
okay there's a relationship between pot
and pot's parts by the way pot is the
picture okay when you say hot uh that
you're talking about you're actually
talking about the picture in your mind
uh and then there is a there is a pot
which is the is the sum total of its
parts roughly there's a pot if you throw
in the seed thing okay but let's not go
there there is pot which is made up of
all the parts of the pot okay there is
such a thing a cart a Chevy or whatever
is the collection the proper uh what do
you call it screwing together of all the
parts of a Chevy and then that's a Chevy
you can call that a Chevy what's its
relationships to it to its parts uh it
depends on those parts okay if you took
away the parts it wouldn't be a shevy
anymore at some point if you tear screws
off the car it's not a Chevy anymore or
at least working Chevy
okay so Chevy doesn't come from its own
side got it and the parts of the Chevy
don't come from their own side got it
does the relationship come from its own
side okay now now see I'm going a little
deeper okay I'll say it again that's the
Chevy come from its own side no do the
parts of the Chevy come from their own
side
no is the relationship between the whole
Chevy and the parts of the
Chevy does that come from its own s is
it a natural
relationship would it always have to be
that way you see that's delicate right
that's
delicate uh and the answer everybody's
not speaking
correctly uh is uh no the relationship
nothing comes from its own side okay but
now you're get into a very delicate
question okay try to hang in
there who was it that Drew a connection
between Chevrolet and the parts of the
Chevrolet it was
me okay it was
me so why I like to say whenever we're
into these deep you know emptiness
things there should be some connection
to your real life if you can't draw some
connection to your real life with this
stuff I don't think it's necessary to
talk about it you know I don't care
about a philosophical point if I can't
use it for my own life okay so how what
what implication does this have for your
life the connection that you draw
between me and your part Hearts is
artificial you've made that connection
it could have been a different
connection the connection between me and
my parts is also flowing from my karmic
seats my perception of a connection
between Mark and this these legs and
arms here is
artificial it's flowing from my karmic
seat it could have been okay ready
here's the application to your real life
it could have
been that my States demanded did I see
a a parts and whole connection between
Mike and his body and my body
together I could call that
mic I could have called that mic you see
the decision that only these parts are
mic is
arbitrary okay it's all right it's not
natural it's not coming from its own
side the connection between Mike and
only these parts is also arbitrary and
artificial and it's not coming from its
own sight it's coming from my seat so
what would
happen if my seeds were different and
they demanded that I draw a connection
between M and two
bodies or 10 or 6
billion see cuz it's artificial it could
have been different you see it's it's
it's
cool okay even the okay I'll say it one
more time even the connection drawn
between Mike and Mike's
Parts it is empty it could have been
different it's just coming from my mind
and a mother who has a child you know I
was with Lama Ora
uh we we there were a couple of a group
of us went to ra you know we we were
fundraising we were fundraising pretas
okay we wanded the world looking for
funds uh and uh so we were being
fundraising Pras in the back of uh Peggy
Hitchcock's car you know I don't know if
you were there I don't
remember uh anyway we were going to take
her out to
dinner you know and trade a $30 dinner
for say $100,000
and uh she's a melon okay so anyway we
took her melon car melon so we we took
her out she's really old she's about 75
or 80 something and Ora had just Lama
Ora had just got had her you know she
was pregnant you know so Lama or was
describing her projects and everything
she was going to be working on you know
and then uh and she said the baby's not
going to change my life at all you know
I'm going to I'm actually going to you
know press I'll just have the baby and
then keep it in a crib and then
uh and then I'll uh you know I'll uh
I'll keep doing my world view world
what's it called knowledge based project
and you know don't worry gu everything
will be the same and Peggy Hitchcock
turns around and he looks at her like
this you know and
go
honey when those hormones take over
you're going to be sitting there
slobbering over this baby for
years you won't even put it down you w't
even put it
down it's true right it happened
uh
why
uh because uh her perception of what
parts were covered by Aura
changed with the bir of the child and as
it often does okay her perception of who
who I
am uh changed when the baby was born you
Peggy would call it hormones right we
would call it karmic sees I guess it's
the same
thing uh but
suddenly uh two two suddenly fourarms
four legs two heads were essentially
Aura okay so so there's no
inherent uh connection between a certain
group of parts and the thing and and and
the thing say Nick or aura or anything
okay the the relationship itself is
pouring from your mind the connection
itself is drawn only by your mind and
there's no natural connection and and
that's why people get what do they call
it serious cognitive
disorders uh maybe you can say autistic
I don't know but I imagine I believe
that their kic seeds are firing in a
different way and they might connect the
edge of the pine tree to the window and
call it something else you see what I
mean and then they have trouble relating
to us you know uh CU we're we're drawing
the connection differently we all have
the karmic
seeds to separate the edge of the pine
tree from the window but that's not not
a natural thing it's an artificial thing
it could would have been that you always
connect the side of the tree to the
window and call it twindo or something
now you know what I mean you laugh but
all your words are
similarly funky you know your words are
also similarly funky you're just used to
them and you found a group of people who
have the same seeds as you luckily you
know and then when you get married and
then after a year that
stops and uh
and you have different words for
different things you divide objects
differently okay all right you
know so here here comes the scripture
he says let's talk about your last life
and this life okay your life last life
and this
life uh let's talk about the body and
mind you had in your last life and the
body and mind you had in this life okay
do they have a
relationship do they have a relationship
I guess you know you say that's my that
was my last life body that was my last
life mind right so must be some
connection his last life body and mind I
don't call my last life body and mind
okay Naturally Speaking okay is is the
mic from this life and what I was in my
last life are they one life or two
separate lives that's the question he's
asking them are they one life or two
separate lives naturally he throws in
the adverb okay he throws in the
adverb are they are they one life or two
lives okay here we
go if you don't believe in the last life
I think it's just kind of naive I mean
uh
go go be with aura Ora's baby for like
15 minutes you know and tell me all that
developed in in the last 365 days
anyway if if your last life's body and
mind are
naturally this life's body and
mind then since you might have been an
animal
in your past life which is defined in
tibetan as Len cuk Len
means do we want the politically correct
translation or the actual one uh Len
cook means
uh stupid and incapable of expressing
themselves which is the which is the
definition of an animal in in in
Buddhism okay and then you're like what
about dolphins gy Michael I'm like well
look dolphins are getting slaughtered by
the Japanese trawlers because they can't
figure out how to get around them okay
they're
dumb okay and they suffer for it and
their their species is is becoming
extinct okay uh they they have
a on a tantric level they could well be
tantric da and and they are on a non-
tantric level they have a lesser
intelligence than than people do and and
therefore they suffer generally animals
suffer more than people they're in a
constant state of Terror you why do you
think birds fly away when you're
approach them did you ever wonder you
know they're afraid of you they they
think any moving thing within 100 yards
might kill them and it will because it's
sometimes a cat Okay so so they just run
from everything to be safe you know and
they spend their whole life looking over
their shoulder it's terrible to be an
animal it's not this uh happy bunny
existence okay they are terrorized they
are in a constant state of Terror that
someone will eat them and they do okay
so
anyway if if this life if this lies you
is the same as L lies you in a natural
way okay the relationship is
natural then then since you have been an
animal in your past lives you you should
in this life be dumb and mute dumb and
mute okay all
right if if your last life and this life
are are one
naturally or conversely since you are
currently enjoying the relative ease of
a human
existence then the dog that you used to
be should should have had some
Comfort okay cuz you the same naturally
the two lives are one
naturally so if if in this life you
enjoy some human Comforts they should
spread back to the dog that you were
before and that dog should have some
human Compass okay if your two lives are
connected in a natural way
okay but let's say that that me in this
life and me in my last life do not share
a natural connection what if we are
naturally separate
okay then he quotes
thear J means
J means Jo and
Sam okay Joe and Sam it's just two he
picked two words out
of out of two common names okay Jo and
Sam if things if if you and your last if
if you and the what you if you and who
you used to be are as different as Joe
and Sam okay two people in this room say
okay if you're as different as
[Music]
that uh if you are not a single mental
Continuum okay if you are not the
continuation of who you were in your
past life all right so because because
now we're talking about naturally
separate
right if there were such a thing as you
being naturally separate from who you
were in the way that John is separate
from Allison
okay uh then it would be incorrect to
say they had they were the same
being okay if if who I was in my past
life and who I am now are as separate
and different as John is from Allison at
the present moment
then then you'd have to say that we
couldn't have been one person who who
got reborn I wouldn't have any
connection with who I used to be okay if
we're just two SE completely separate
people you couldn't say that was my last
life if we're totally separate okay if
we're not separate he should be
experiencing the pleasures of my life if
we are separate then you can't say that
was me got it right
naturally try to draw your mind to this
question because it doesn't only apply
to your past life and your present life
it applies to who you were before you
drove to Prescott and who you are at
Prescott okay who was that who got in
the car to or in the airplane to go to
Prescott and what's their relationship
to you now okay do they have a
relationship are are are are you are you
them later in time
or are you separate from
them are you disconnected to that to
that person who got into the car to come
to Prescot or are you the same
person and if you say you're the same or
if you say you're separate is that is
that separateness or sameness natural or
could it have been
different is it coming from its own side
that separateness or that sameness is
that coming from its own side you have
to say no okay but then you get into
this same thing if you say the
connection between me and the person I
was yesterday okay try to try to hang in
there okay this is heavy stuff it's
going to save your life okay try to hang
in there is there a connection between
me and the person I was yesterday are we
the same person or are we separate
people okay and is that separateness not
natural or could it have been different
or could I could I reasonably think that
I was two people before or that I could
be two people tomorrow could
mic could the mic of today whose parts
are only these tomorrow be a person
whose parts are are twice as many is it
possible is it possible and then what
would be the relationship between us no
mic one developed into mic
2 and
then who draws a connection between what
I'm going to be tomorrow and who I am
today you know where is that
connection yeah what reality doesn't
have where did it come from why do I
think I was in this sixth grade in
Maryland Elementary School on Glendale
Avenue in Phoenix you know why do I
think
that and is it true
okay or or did I have a totally
different
path is it true who you think you
were cuz if it's not true means true
means uh what does true mean
real does that connection between me and
the kid in sixth grade in Maryland
Elementary School is that connection
natural and necessary or is it is it
what do you call it
malleable could it change if my seeds
changed could I draw a different
connection between me and my past could
I rewrite my history is it perhaps the
case that every teacher at Maryland
Elementary School was a tting daddy and
that there was
where and that they were setting me up
for something now
okay is it could I rewrite that
connection you
see if the connection is there from its
own side I can't they were just
underpaid nice people
okay uh but if that connection between
me and sixth grade Michael is not
natural if that connection is coming
from my own
mind then with the right seeds I could
perceive that every
figure in my childhood who influenced me
was in truth a TC Dy trying to get me
here you see you see if the connection's
not natural if the connection is being
drawn by my
mind then you can rewrite your
past uh validly okay without make
believe without making it up you can
validly rewrite your past and and
frankly intan terms you can establish
logically that the teachers that you had
in your Elementary School were in fact
Buddhas who who wanted you to be
here
okay that also applies your high school
boyfriend of course you know
that I mean that's the important one
okay uh
so he starts listing problems that would
arise If You Were Somehow separate from
who you have been okay problems that
would arise If You Were Somehow separate
from who you have been in a natural way
okay in an incontrovertible
way here's one problem how could you
remember your
past how could you remember who you have
been if you're separate in the way that
that John and Alison are you know if you
if you are naturally separate from who
you used to be how can you remember who
you've been right he quotes you know
cases where people have remembered their
past lives but I don't think you have in
an American audience you don't have to
go that way you could just go to sixth
grade okay how could you remember who
you were in sixth grade if you are
essentially different or disconnected
from that person okay
he's quing again okay I'll read the the
lines of AR which are kind of hard but
then he he explains them clearly for us
okay if I am essentially different from
who I used to be
if I am as separate from mikee in the
sixth grade as John is currently from
Allison okay two different people if I
am two different
people
uh then that would also have to not
exist okay
what uh memories of who I used to be
okay why are we talking about this is
there a mik who has been sustained since
the sixth grade okay is there a Mike who
is somehow separate from his body and
mind who has been going on since the
sixth grade independent of his body and
mind you see body and mind have changed
drastically but is there some Uber mic
that has been you know going the whole
time all right that's the question
right the same would apply to his
uh to his living to his dying to is
being born we'll we'll get there okay
here comes the sex part you were waiting
for this right
uh there would be a
disconnection and then Karma could
be Karma could just go away chwa is a
very powerful word just go away meaning
is it possible to do a kindness or a or
a meanness to another person plant a
seed in your mind and just vaguely hope
that it kind of forgets to ripen you
see do is it the case that some of the
Deeds you do are not well recorded and
and don't flower in in in exactly just
ways or is it the case that everyone is
just you know
inevitably will will create the same
thing for you that you gave to somebody
else you see it's a principle of Karma
that no karma is ever lost it's a closed
system it's an
ecology okay Karma cannot be lost
everything you do everything you say
everything you think comes back to you
and must come back to you in
space okay there's no there's no what do
you call
it God can't cut you a break you know
God can't say uh oh gee let's just
cancel that abortion you know what I
mean hey why why do you want me to
cancel the abortion this is God talking
uh cuz I was
dumb uh cuz I shouldn't have done it uh
cuz I feel bad about it uh cuz I really
don't want to experience the result of
that you know I mean that's your
thinking right you think like that but
karma is just chwa chwa means uh you
never get out of anything nobody can cut
you a break there's no being who can cut
you a break you get what you give if you
want to be the beneficiary of that
principle you have to live with the neg
the downside of it also okay like
everybody wants more money how do you
get money give money to other people how
do I get healthy serve the sick how do I
get strong and attractive be patient you
know and then they like they like okay
I'm going to be patient I'm going to
help the sick I'm going to give money
and you you can't go up to people like
that and say oh by the way it do doesn't
work all the time then they'll get upset
right they'll say this is unjust right
then you say then they come up to you
and say I had an abortion do you think
anything will happen to
me and then you're like aren't you the
person who asked me yesterday about the
money thing you know whether it would
always work and I they said yeah I asked
you yesterday if giving money would
always work and what did I say oh you
said it would always work you said all
kic seats always work so why are you
coming me today and asking me for an
exemption
on something bad you did okay there's no
exemptions Karma always ripens Karma
unless you do the four powers that
you're going to learn on
Thursday okay anyway if me and Mike in
the sixth grade we essentially separate
in the way that John and Allison are at
this current moment then
Karma he could screw around and I don't
have to worry about it you know he could
do what ever whatever he did has been
canceled because I'm an essentially
different
person okay all right got it we didn't
get there yet
okay and then you'd also have the
problem that Karma's committed by
Allison would have to ripen on
John okay karmas committed by Allison
would have to ripen on John if it's
possible if I am essentially separate
from Mike in the sixth grade but I still
have to
experience the results of what he
did then then by that logic uh the
things that Allison did could r on
John
okay uh
de uh hang in there we got like 10 more
minutes
okay so then you would have if if
Mike is essentially
separate from who he was in the sixth
grade in the sense of two separate
people then there's the problem that the
Deeds that Mike and the sixth grade did
would never come to fruition okay so
I'll ask you a
question uh given the proper
circumstances given you know given
normal
circumstances is there ever a Karma
which doesn't Ren
I mean can't you just die with a lot of
karmas left and they're
canceled think about how you think about
Karma think about how you think about
Karma okay think about how you think
about karma is it your opinion that upon
death all deaths are
canceled you like to think that a little
bit right I mean no you just like to
think I start over with a clean slate
you know if I go on at
all I certainly go on with a clear slate
okay the fact is you approach death with
billions upon billions of of unripened
kic seeds in your mind okay every one of
us approaches death with countless of
remaining seeds in our
mind their ripening takes precedence
over your
dime okay their ripening takes
precedence over your dying your dying
cannot stop them from
ripening okay your Dy the death of your
body cannot stop the seeds from ripening
they will ripen okay that the end of
your body has no effect on their
ripening okay they must ripen and they
will ripen and they will ripen as a new
body they will ripen as a new life and
you you can't you you can't get out of
it okay even if you die you can't get
out of it okay death and taxes
right uh we got to pay my taxes J me
uh okay the the seeds will assert
themselves whether you are still alive
or not okay they will create a new life
got it seeds
are the your all the karmas you've done
in the past have to ripen and if and if
even if you want to be dead you can't be
dead okay no people ask me should I
commit Comm suicide said if if it helped
let's all do it you know but it doesn't
help cuz you still have all those seeds
and they assert themselves and you have
a different body in a different place
and it's probably going to be worse cuz
you killed
yourself
okay cuz that's a bad deed you destroyed
a you destroyed someone's chance for
enlightenment whose mine okay all right
okay um where are we
so let's say you commit suicide with the
idea that okay a person who believes in
rebirth commits suicide believing that
who they will be and who they are now
are are essentially separate are
naturally separate
okay that would make sense
right uh if I'm Not Who if I'm not the
mik iy was in sixth
grade then it would make sense if I had
collected a lot of bad Deeds I could
just kill myself now and you know some
other guy will have to experience those
results all
right okay so one of the principles of
karma is uh
say you can't
say means any time you commit an action
you must you must encounter the result
there's no choice you must okay you will
okay
but uh if it were the case that
Mike again why are we talking about it
we're trying to find out where Nick is
we're just trying to find out where Nick
is does Nick cover all the Nicks he's in
his life does the current Nick cover all
the Nicks he's been in his life and if
he
does is is that Nick does that Nick own
all the parts he's ever
been
okay is there an
ubernick you know and then you know it's
kind of weird because now he has to
shave and before he didn't have to
sh and now you know what I mean okay
he's covering two
cheeks one that didn't have whiskers yet
and one which does have
whiskers so it all gets weird is is he
the Nick who didn't have fuzz my dad
came to me in the hippie days he said
okay God damn it I don't care if you
grow SS but they look straggly you know
cuz you're too young and it's just these
like three threads kind of you know he
said wait a few years you know and
uh but uh
so whose cheeks who whose cheeks are
mine you see I mean the ones who didn't
have hairs are the ones who have too
many here you know who which ones are me
okay all right we're trying to find Nick
why because because Nick has spent a lot
of time defending Nick and and and
suffering because of it if we can
clarify who Nick
is then uh Nick won't
Nick won't get angry when someone yells
at him and then he'll reach nirvana and
then he'll change right okay if we can
find out if we can separate the Nick
who's not there from the Nick who is
there all right we're still trying to
separate the Nick who's not there from
the Nick who is there okay here we
go okay so if Nick if this Nick is not
the Nick who was here
yesterday then
uh and if the Nick now still had to what
do you call it dang if this Nick had to
experience the
karma of Nick yesterday Nick yesterday
was naughty then Nick today has to
experience the result of
that but if the Nick today is not the
Nick he was yesterday okay then it's
unfair then a person would have to
experience a result when they hadn't
done anything
okay if this Nick is not the Nick he was
yesterday then it would be unfair
because this Nick would be experiencing
karmic results that he didn't have to do
with cuz that was yesterday's
new okay which is also
illegal he's concluding the third of the
four essential points that you should
understand if you're going to
understand who you're not okay who
you're not there are four points
for uh first one was who what is the
gaka who's the Nick that's not
there what's the Nick that's not there
like what's the Nick that's not there
like okay I'm I'm searching for The
Emptiness of Nick if I find the
emptiness of Nick I can become an
enlightened being to find the emptiness
of Nick I have to find the Nick who's
not there I have to identify the Nick
who's not there who I always thought was
there got it that's the first one the
second one was I got to look for Nick
Nick is
either Nick is either his parts or he's
the sum total of his Parts I I I'm going
to look for Nick either in his parts or
in the sum total of his Parts Nick is
either plural or Nick is
one okay he's either he either is his
parts or he's the Nick that we say has
his Parts okay because there's no place
else Nick could be so we just finished
uh understanding that Nick either
has who you think Nick is either has to
be his parts or he has to be someone who
owns his Parts got it that's the second
Point there's no other choice if there's
a Nick he's either got to be his parts
or he's got to be someone who possesses
his Parts like ubernick okay and we and
number three we just finished destroying
the idea that ubernick could exist
there's no
Nick by now you should be like totally
convinced or asleep okay you can have a
choice totally convinced uh there is no
niit who is naturally the sum of his
Parts there's no such
Nick there's no one Nick who's
controlling his body and
mind because there's too many problems
with
that and and frankly this is the one
that we tend to number three is the one
that we tend to have trouble with We
Believe Nick is his is the combination
of his part of his body and mind and we
believe a car is the combination of its
parts you know you ask somebody what's a
car you say well it's a tire it's four
tires it's two axles it's a one driving
steering wheel it's a front windshield
it's a back you name all the parts and
you say all of that together is a car is
it tell me the right answer you get to
go to wherever you're going a break I
guess if you put all the parts of a car
together you know properly screw them
together in the right way is
is that a
car then you have to say no or you don't
at least you have to shake your head
it's not a car
why it's not a c so you think of it as a
car
right okay if you put all the pieces of
a pen together is not a
pen then you have to
say okay no because it could be seen
differently those pieces put together
could be seen differently I know people
who's only relationship with cars is to
use them to plant flowers in you know
they have no interest in driving or
owning a car uh they just when they look
at a car they're like God look how many
places you could plant some flowers you
know you take off the top and you know
they don't see a car they don't see a
means of transportation they see a
flower
pot
okay
uh so it's not true that all of Nick's
Parts together is knit
naturally you have to use that word you
have to add that word natural without my
kic
seeds synthesizing it that way he he's
not the sum of his
Parts he's not one thing which possesses
all his parts that that was Point number
three and we finished it just
now all those gymnastics were to
prove that Nick is not all of Nick's
Parts until you think of Nick that way
forced to do so by your own past Deeds
by your own past kindness to other which
is to say in the new roach system of
science uh Nick is a product of my
kindness okay Nick is not a product of
certain chemicals or enzymes or or eggs
or sperms or you see he is solely a
product of my own kindness okay and if I
haven't been so kind he'll be
grumpy and and uh irritating okay and if
I've been kind uh he will be a nice
person as as he is okay all right that's
all that's all there is no one Nick
who's
naturally a combination of his parts
that's the part we just finished what do
you think is going to be last part
number
four there is no
Nick who's other than his Parts together
what do you think Nick Nick is his arm
or Nick is his legs is there any other
choice by the way
I'll give you the two choices I stated
so
far Nick is the sum total of all his
parts here's a second choice Nick isn't
the sum total of all his Parts he's he's
just one of his parts or some of his
Parts Nick's arm is Nick
okay that's a second choice what tonapa
and AR and Lord budha didn't even
mention another Choice what would be
another
Choice yeah is Nick uh Sheree's arms and
legs
because that's just crazy okay all right
we don't even go there all we have to
prove is that Nick is not the sum of the
parts of
Nick and Nick is not just his arm or
just his ear or just his nose and then
we can establish that there's no Nick in
those parts okay there's no Nick the way
we used to think okay independent of of
my kindness there's no Nick independent
of my kindness this exercise three and
four is meant to prove that there's no
Nick who is independent of my kindness
towards others